上溯至宇宙初始 周遭还只是一片漆黑
In the beginning, there was darkness.
不知何时 忽地一声巨响
And then... Bang!
时间空间以及物质皆由此发端
Giving birth to an endless expanding existence
此后不断膨胀 延伸 永无止境
of time, space, and matter.
每一天 新的发现都在不断为我们解开
Every day, new discoveries are unlocking
蕴藏于这里的那些神秘莫测
the mysterious, the mind-blowing,
令人大开眼界 致命的秘密
the deadly secrets of a place we call
我们称这个地方为"宇宙"
the universe.
在宇宙里 了解最靠近你的邻居很重要
In the universe, it's important to know your nearest neighbors.
可是对我们这个银河角落
But how much do we really know about our corner
我们真正了解多少？
of the Milky Way?
就在几年前
In just the last few years,
科学家发现了潜藏在我们后院的
scientists have uncovered incredible secrets
惊人秘密:
lurking in our own backyard:
新卫星 新行星以及新奥秘
new moons, new planets, and new mysteries.
这就象你的邻居有一座房子
It's like there was a house in your neighborhood
但你从不知道
that you never knew was there.
你会遇到一些
Meet new neighbors
恰好经过的新邻居
who are just passing through...
有些行星在银河里漫无目的地流浪
There are planets that are wandering the galaxy aimlessly
没有自己的家
without a place to call home.
而有些老朋友
And old friends
则时日无多
whose days are numbered.
相信参宿四会在今晚
It's conceivable that Betelgeuse
演进为超新星
will go supernova tonight.
让我们展开旅程
Join us for a tour of the neighborhood
现在就去认识这个地区
we're only now getting to know.
它就是"银河里的我们地区"
This is "Our Place in the Milky Way."
宇宙:银河里的我们地区
这不是你的地区
This isn't your neighborhood,
不论是这个
neither is this
还是这个
or this
或这些的任何一个
or any of these.
甚至这个也不是
And it isn't even this.
从广义来说
Looked at from a wider perspective,
你的地区是一团巨大的气体云
your neighborhood is a big cloud of gas.
天文学家把
Astronomers say the solar system
太阳系正在穿越的本星际云
is moving through the local interstellar cloud,
也称为"本地绒毛"
also called "the local fluff"
因为它密度低且形状不规则
because of its low density and irregular shape.
气体主要是氢 以及一些氦
The gases are mainly hydrogen and some helium.
还有微量的较重的原子
There are trace amounts of heavier atoms
比如在星际介质边缘漂浮着的
like carbon and oxygen and nitrogen
碳 氧和氮
that are just floating around the interstellar medium.
我们知道 星际介质里较重的原子
We know that the heavier atoms in the interstellar medium
是超新星之类的恒星
are left over from
发生爆炸而遗留下来的
previous explosions of stars as supernovae.
本星际云团长达30光年
The local fluff is 30 light-years long,
大约是180万亿英里
about 180 trillion miles.
它位于一个被称为"本地泡"的烟囱状
It's inside a larger chimney-shaped gas cloud
巨大气体云内部
called the local bubble,
那也是一个古老的超新星遗留下来的
also the remnant of an ancient supernova.
本地泡长300光年
The bubble is 300 light-years long
位于银河一个旋臂的内缘
and lies in the inner edge of one of the spiral arms of the Milky Way.
这就是我们的地区
And that's our neighborhood.
至少 我们认为它是
At least, we think it is.
我们在银河系里的精确位置
Our exact position in the Milky Way galaxy
与某些未知的臂有关
relative to the arms actually isn't known.
银河的构造难以说清
The structure of the galaxy is not known in any real detail.
一些人认为有两个主臂
Some people think there are two major arms.
有人认为有四个主臂
Some people think there are four major arms.
我们难以确定
It's hard for us to determine
我们银河的精确结构
the exact structure of our Milky Way,
这些臂在哪里等等
where all the arms are and so on,
因为如同迷宫里的老鼠
because it's kind of like a mouse being inside a maze.
你不能掌控全局
You don't get the big picture.
在地球上 在任意地区
In almost any Earth neighborhood,
你都能非常精确地确定位置
you can determine your location very precisely.
30英尺后转左
Turn left in 30 feet.
但是 当面对银河
But when you're dealing with something
这样的庞然大物时
as big as the Milky Way,
GPS就不行了
GPS isn't an option.
银河的跨度为100 000光年
The galaxy is, you know, 100,000 light-years across.
即使是在我们地区探索
Even exploring our local neighborhood
也有许多的不确定
involves a lot of uncertainty.
但如果有银河坐标系统
But if we did have a galactic positioning system,
也许能让我们在银河的
it would probably locate us about midway between
顶部和底部之间
the top and bottom of the Milky Way
以及内外缘之间
and about midway between the galaxy's outer edge
进行定位
and inner core.
我们太阳系离银河中心
Our solar system is about 26,000 light-years away
大约26 000光年
from the center of our galaxy.
根据一个假说 我们拥有
According to one hypothesis,
一个非常独特的位置
we have a very exclusive location.
有一种看法认为 只有在
There is one idea that only stars in a certain range
恒星与银河中心的距离为某一范围时
of distances from the center of our galaxy
它才在所谓的银河适宜居住区之内
are in the so-called galactic habitable zone,
这就是说 环绕这些恒星旋转的行星
that is, able to have life on planets
才能拥有生命
surrounding those stars.
它正是这样的好地方
It is just the right place
有温度适宜的恒星
with a star of the right temperature
行星恰好位于
and a planet at the right distance
表面能有许多液态水的距离上
for there to be a lot of liquid water on the surface,
生命化学物质出现并演化成我们人类
where the chemistry of life began and evolved into us.
整个的银河适宜居住地带
The overall range of the galactic habitable zone
从距离银河中心13 000光年的地方延伸到
extends from about 13,000 to 35,000 light-years
35 000光年的地方
from the center of the Milky Way.
主要的部分 是我们的所在地
The main part, where we are,
处于距离中心20 000至29 000光年的范围内
ranges from 20,000 to 29,000 light-years from the core.
在这个地带里
Inside the zone,
旧区的消亡
old neighborhoods have been destroyed
造就了一个我们称为家园的地方
to make a place we can call home.
受观察角度的影响
Depending upon how you look at things,
如果从全局去观察宇宙
our local neighborhood, our local solar system,
与看起来将要发生的事来作比较 你可以认为
is actually a relatively safe place
我们这个地区 我们太阳系
compared to what seems to be going on
是一个相对安全的地方
if you look at the universe in the large.
但在太阳系的早期
In the early history of our solar system,
它是非常动荡的地方
it was a much more violent place.
构成太阳和行星的物质
And the material that formed the Sun and the planets
还在忙着安顿自己
was still sorting itself out.
五花八门的碰撞
There were all sorts of collisions
层出不穷的动乱
and violent things happening
形成了我们今天这个
that gave rise to this nice, calm
美好 平静或者说是相对平静的地方
or relatively calm place that we have today.
我们认为最早的恒星
We think that the earliest stars formed
只由氢和氮所构成
out of hydrogen and helium alone,
但是 在长年累月之后 这些恒星
but that, over time, the stars work as these processors
不断产生重元素
that create the heavier elements.
这一点至关重要 因为当这些恒星
This is important because when those stars
最终死亡和爆炸时
eventually die and explode,
这些超新星或死亡星球的爆炸
these supernovae, or stellar death explosions,
为银河和周围的物质
seed the galaxy and the material around it
带来了重元素
with heavier elements.
比方说 我们细胞里的碳
So for example, the carbon in our cells,
呼吸的氧
the oxygen that we breathe,
骨头里的钙
the calcium in our bones,
红细胞里的铁
the iron in our red blood cells,
所有这些都是重元素
all those are heavy elements.
我们知道
We know that the Sun
太阳至少是第二 三代的恒星
is at least a second or a third-generation star
因为有许多行星围绕着它
because there are planets around it.
有许多由铁 碳和其它重元素构成的东西
There are things made of iron and carbon and other heavier elements.
但是 造就地球生命的过程
But the processes that led to life on Earth
在这个地带之外似乎看不到
don't seem to exist outside the zone.
紧挨银河边缘的地方
Closer to the edge of the galaxy,
有几个大恒星已经爆炸
fewer massive stars have exploded,
产生了不太多的重元素
producing fewer heavy elements.
在银河外层较远的地方
Further out in the galaxy,
你找不到象碳 氮和氧
you don't have as many atoms like carbon, nitrogen, oxygen
这些对生命化学物质非常重要的原子
the atoms that are so important for the chemistry of life.
所以 银河适宜居住地带
So the habitable zone of the galaxy
以是否拥有构成生命的重元素
cuts off at a distance where you just won't have
作为分界线
the heavier atoms to make life.
如果银河外层是不好的地区
If the outer galaxy is a bad neighborhood,
那么内层有过之而无不及
the inner area is even worse.
巨大气体行星的大质量产生的万有引力
Gravity from massive gas giant planets
能够把我们撕碎
could tear us apart.
而且 如果再靠近银河中心
And there are other dangers the closer you get
还会有其它危险
to the galactic core.
在哥白尼时代
Back in the times of Copernicus,
我们自认是宇宙的中心
we thought that we were the center of our universe,
甚至在开始进一步研究天空的时候
and even as we started to learn more about the heavens,
人们最终还是认为自己是银河的中心
eventually, we still thought that we were the center of the galaxy.
现在我们知道得更多了
Now that we know even more, though,
但是 我们应当庆幸
it actually turns out that we're lucky
我们不是在银河的中心
we're not in the center of the galaxy.
在银河中心
At the center of the Milky Way,
人马座A星正在疯狂吞噬物质
sucking matter and even light into it,
即使是光也会被吸进去
is Sagittarius A-Star,
它是跨度接近一千四百万英里的一个黑洞
a black hole nearly 14 million miles across
质量是太阳的370万倍
with a mass 3.7 million times that of our Sun.
如果银河中心有一个黑洞在里面
If the galactic center has a black hole in it,
它会放射出大量的辐射
it gives off a lot of radiation
足以摧毁生命
enough to fry life as we know it
所以你不能太靠近它
so you can't be too close to that.
此外 在银河里
Then there are other regions in the galaxy
也有其它不太有利于生命的区域
that are also probably not so great for life
因为那里有非常大量的
because there's just so much radiation
从附近炽热的O-型星传来的辐射
from nearby really hot O-type stars.
O-型星是宇宙巨人
O-type stars are giants.
它们比太阳更热
They're hotter than the Sun,
质量是太阳的10至50倍
10 to 50 times as massive,
会释放出非常大量的紫外线
and throw out titanic amounts of ultraviolet radiation.
面对这些恒星 你要担心的不是晒伤
With these stars, you don't worry about sunburn
而是毁灭
but extinction.
大量O-型星簇拥着你
It's probably not easy to survive in an environment
这样的环境 恐怕你不能轻易存活
where you're in a tight cluster with a lot of O-type stars.
O-型巨星能够在行星形成之前
O-type giants can destroy planets
就摧毁它们
before they form.
这些恒星的辐射如此之强
The radiation from these stars is so strong
可以从即将成形的行星那里
that it actually sweeps the material away
把物质扫走
from these newly forming, would-be planetary systems
并从它们的恒星轨道上狠狠抛出去
and rips it out of the orbit of their stars.
如果你需要证明 那就看看玫瑰星云吧
If you want proof, look at the Rosette nebula.
它离本地泡非常远 相隔5 200光年
It's 5,200 light-years away, far outside the local bubble,
但它能展示O-型星会为我们地区带来什么影响
but it shows what O-type giants could do to our neighborhood.
2008年亚利桑那州的一份研究表明
A 2008 study by the University of Arizona
在星云中发现有1 000个恒星
of 1,000 stars in the nebula
因为太靠近蓝巨星
found star after star had been made barren
而成为不毛之地
by being too close to a blue giant.
那么 对于O-型巨星的辐射
So what's a safe distance from the radiation
距离多远才安全呢？
of an O-type giant?
如果你问我
Well, if you ask me,
我会说 你到哪里都没用
you can never be too far away from a giant.
但如果你象我们地球生命
If you're life like us here on Earth
习惯了温顺的太阳一样习惯了它
we're used to our fairly tame Sun
你还得距离它至少数十光年
you want to be probably at least tens of light-years away,
或许比这还远
maybe more than that.
真的 别太近
Really, just don't get too close.
正如沙漠与海洋之间的城市
Like a city between a desert and an ocean,
我们这个银河角落在两个不同的
our corner of the galaxy thrives
不适宜居住地带之间繁荣发展
between two different inhospitable regions.
拥有生命的力量
With the elements of life
却没有强辐射的威胁
and without the threat of intense radiation,
看起来我们地区
it seems like our neighborhood
似乎是唯一能居住的地方
is literally the only place to live.
但我们这个地方在银河里
But is our place in the Milky Way
真的独一无二？
really so exclusive?
关于银河适宜居住地带的看法是
The idea of the galactic habitable zone is that
如果太靠近银河中心
if you're too close to the center of the galaxy,
那里的极端环境
there's all these crazy things going on,
会扼杀生命
and it tends to kill off life.
坦白说 我很怀疑这个观点
To be honest, I'm personally skeptical of the idea
我认为生命会发生在
because I think that life can happen
各种环境里
in all sorts of environments,
退一步来说 在不确切的情况下
or at the very least, we don't know,
我们要放开思想
so we should be open-minded.
可能我们这种生命
It's possible that our kind of life
只能在这个银河宜居地带生活
can only live in this galactic habitable zone,
但会有我们称为极端生物的
but elsewhere, there could be other kinds of life
其它种类的生命在别处
that we would call extremophiles.
反过来 他们会把我们称为极端生物
On the other hand, they would call us extremophiles.
有一件事是必然的
One thing is certain.
在我们地区 我们有一个
In our neighborhood, we have a sun that,
与蓝巨星不同的太阳
unlike a blue giant,
以我们尚在研究的各种方式
protects us from danger and destruction
来保护我们免受危险和毁灭
in ways that we're still learning about.
它的保护可能是隐形的
That protection may be invisible,
如果失去太阳的保护
but if we lose the Sun's protection,
我们地区的末日就会降临
our neighborhood could be doomed.
在银河里的我们这个地方 似乎相当安宁
Our place in the Milky Way seems pretty peaceful
因为 就象许多社区
because, like a lot of communities,
坏人被24小时工作的保安系统拒之门外了
we don't give much thought to the 24/7 security systems
我们不需要大伤脑筋
that keep the bad stuff away.
许多在河畔或海滨的城市
Many cities on the edges of rivers or oceans
组织人力物力去建筑堤坝 以防止洪灾
have dams and levies to protect them from floods.
如果堤坝不行
If the dams and levies fail
灾难就会降临
disaster.
银河系里的我们 也是威胁与保护共存
We've got threats and defenses on a galactic scale too.
太空充斥着被称为宇宙射线的辐射
Space is filled with radiation known as cosmic rays.
宇宙射线对我们的危害程度
Cosmic rays are bad for us in the same sense
等同于地球上的核辐射
that nuclear radiation here on Earth would be bad for us,
因为高能辐射
because high-energy radiation
会让构成我们人类的
tends to dissociate carbon bonds,
碳化合物分离
which is what we're made of.
你的DNA会被破坏
What you're really doing is damaging your DNA,
而且有可能
and there's a potential there
因此而开始产生变异
that you could start to have mutations based off of that.
变异会帮助物种生存
Some mutations can help a species survive
也会导致它灭绝
or lead to extinction.
没有证据表明
There's no evidence that cosmic radiation
宇宙辐射过去曾对地球有负面影响
has really negatively impacted Earth in the past,
但你不能视之为无物
but it's nothing that you want to play around with.
我们对抗宇宙射线的
Our neighborhood's prime defense
有力防御是
against cosmic rays:
磁力
magnetism.
这是我们的防御带
We have this zone of protection in our neighborhood.
当然 地球拥有磁场
Of course, the Earth has a magnetic field
归功于地核内的事物如何运动
due to how things move around in the core of the Earth.
太阳也有一个强大的磁场
The Sun also has a powerful magnetic field,
也因此而拥有太阳风
and it also has the solar wind.
这些现象形成了对我们的各种保护
These phenomena actually generate ways of protecting us
避免从太阳系外面而来的侵害
from things that come from outside the solar system.
太阳磁场被太阳风
The Sun's magnetic field is twisted
扭曲
by the solar wind,
带电质子和电子源源不断地
streams of charged protons and electrons
以一百万英里的时速从太阳发射出来
that shoot out of the Sun at a million miles an hour.
于是 太阳系行星之间的微粒
And then the particles that live in the solar system between the planets
沿着周围的磁力线
actually stretch the lines of the magnetic field around
形成复杂的图案
in complicated patterns.
携带磁场的太阳风
The solar wind carries the magnetic field
比海王星轨道的三倍
more than three times farther out
还要长
than the orbit of Neptune.
然而 在90亿英里外
But 9 billion miles away,
在一个被称为"太阳驻点"的地方
at a place called the heliopause,
太阳风失去动力 几乎没有速度
the solar wind runs out of steam and slows to almost nothing.
在慢下来时 它扭曲太阳磁场成为一道屏障
As it slows, it twists the Sun's magnetic field
抵挡从星际空间而来的
into a barrier against cosmic rays
宇宙射线
from interstellar space.
这个区域被称为"日鞘"
This is the heliosheath.
如果没有日鞘
If it wasn't for the heliosheath,
宇宙射线会一直不停地涌入我们太阳系
these cosmic rays would actually pour into our solar system all the time.
对这些可能影响我们地球
The heliosheath acts as a kind of shark cage
来势汹汹的宇宙射线
for these incoming cosmic rays
日鞘起着鲨鱼笼的作用
that might otherwise influence our planet.
有一些会穿过来
Some do come through,
但不至于象没有这种保护一样
but they don't come through as strongly as they would
来得那么凶猛
without that protection.
人们一向认为
It used to be thought that the heliosheath
日鞘是由磁力垂帘构成的
was a rather elegant barrier
一道简单实用的屏障
made of flowing curtains of magnetic force,
但最近
but recently,
1977年从地球发射的太空船
enter Voyager 1 and Voyager 2,,
旅行者1号和2号进入了该区域
probes sent out from Earth in 1977.
在21世纪早期
In the early 21st century,
这些70年代的设备发回的信息指出
these disco-era devices sent back information
太阳的磁力线
indicating that the Sun's magnetic field lines
不是光滑地连在一起的
don't flow smoothly together;
它们间断开来 成为狂暴的磁泡
they break up and reform into violent magnetic froth,
磁泡里的每一个泡宽一亿英里
and each bubble in that froth is 100 million miles wide.
通常认为 在它们之间是一道光滑 优雅的屏障
We used to think that it was a smooth, nice barrier
但实际上
between them, but in fact,
那是躁动之地 有各种泡和其它形状的图案
it's a roiling place with all sorts of bubbles and patterns.
我想 总有人把宇宙超乎自然地
I think there's always been people who think the universe
进行美化
is more elegant than it is
或是狂暴化
and people who think it's more violent than it is,
以至于我们总会惊讶于一面或其它面
and we're always surprised one way or the other.
而真相是 宇宙有些方面
The truth is that some aspects of the universe
非常美丽 但在别的方面
are quite elegant, and in other aspects,
它非常糟糕
it's quite a mess.
何处是我们银河地区的美丽地方
Where are the elegant areas of our galactic neighborhood,
何处是狂野之地？
and where are the rough parts?
宇宙里的气体和尘埃让我们难以分辨
It can be hard to tell with all that gas and dust in the cosmos.
这有点象从这里看我身后的好莱坞
It's sort of like looking here behind me at Hollywood.
那里有一个标志性建筑
There's even a landmark there,
"神殿唱片"大厦
the Capitol Records building.
你能勉强地看到它
You can barely make it out.
但在更远处
And even beyond that,
山岗就显得很模糊
there are some hills that are even hazier.
这是因为在空气中有东西妨碍了视线
It's because there's stuff in the air that blocks the view.
山岗本身还让我看不了更远
The hill itself obscures my ability to look beyond it,
这有点象非常稠密的分子云中的尘埃
and that's kind of like the dust in very dense molecular clouds.
充斥着尘埃的稠密的分子云构成一堵厚墙
When you hit a big wall of a dense molecular cloud
让你看不到任何东西
filled with dust, you can't see anything.
我们在探索银河地区时
When we explore our galactic neighborhood,
所见依赖于我们怎样去看
what we see depends on how we look at things.
通过观察天空 我们学到一个历史经验
One of the things we've learned through the history of looking at the sky
任何时候 如果用不同方法去观察
is that every time you look in a different way,
你会看到新东西
you see new things,
而用不同方法观察天空
and looking at the sky a different way
简单地说 往往是指
often simply means looking in a different part
使用不同的电磁波频谱
of the electromagnetic spectrum.
当我们用眼睛仰望天空
As we look up into the sky with our eyes
或是借助于光学望远镜
or with the aid of optical telescopes,
所利用的是光谱的可见部分
in the visible part of the spectrum,
我们对着夜空
we see the night sky,
会看到许多的事物
and there's a lot to see,
但这只是其中的一小部分
but it's only a fraction of what's out there.
某些太空望远镜
Some space telescopes
利用红外线成像来穿透宇宙尘埃
see through cosmic dust with infrared vision,
其原理类似于民用红外摄像机
similar to that used by commercial infrared cameras.
我带来了一个塑料袋
I've brought with me this plastic bag,
当我把手放进袋子里
and when I put my hand inside of the bag,
你看不到我竖起了多少个手指
you can't see how many fingers I'm holding up.
利用红外摄像机
With the infrared camera,
你能够看到我身体散发的热量
you can see the heat coming off my body,
我的脸部 比较暖和 呈红白色
so my face, which is warm, is red and white,
但是我的头发 比较低温 明显呈蓝色
but my hair, which is cool, shows up as blue.
因此 利用红外摄像机 你能辩认出
So with the infrared camera, you should be able to make out
我竖起了多少个手指
how many fingers I'm holding up,
哪怕你不能看穿这个塑料袋
even though you can't see through this bag.
这就是天文学家为什么能穿透宇宙尘埃
That's how astronomers peer through cosmic dust
去观察隐藏在视线之后的事物
when they want to see things that are hidden from sight.
例如 正在形成的恒星非常热
For example, stars being born are very warm,
但它们被尘埃遮蔽
but they're obscured by dust shells.
利用红外线 我们就能看到它们
With infrared, we can see them.
某些物体透明或不透明
Certain objects are transparent or opaque
依赖于试图穿透它们的
depending upon the frequency of the light
光的频率
that's trying to get through them.
所以 在事实上 碍事的东西
And so, in fact, something that's getting in the way,
比如诸多的星际尘埃或气体
like a lot of interstellar dust or gas,
妨碍着望远镜的观测
is getting in the way of what your telescopes can see,
但如果利用光谱的其它部分 那它们便化为无形
are actually invisible in another part of the spectrum.
你就能看到背后的东西
You can see what's behind.
利用红外线
With infrared
和诸多我们可以自由支配的其它波段
and a multitude of other wavelengths at our command,
我们发现了许多我们过去不知道的邻居
we've discovered a lot of neighbors we didn't know we had.
如果你能用光谱的一个特殊波段去看
There's a whole array of instrumentation
你就能用一个非常特殊的方式去观察天空
which is exploiting that lesson that if you look
有一个仪器阵列
in a particular part of the spectrum,
就是利用这个原理去工作的
you see the sky in a very particular way.
从既往的研究来看
From what we've observed,
在一些新邻居意欲
it looks like some old neighbors might have helped
彻底摧毁我们的时候
life form on Earth,
似乎一些老邻居可能对地球生命的形成
while some newer neighbors may be planning
有过帮助
to wipe us out.
在探索银河系里的我们这个地方时
As we've explored our place in the Milky Way,
我们曾遇到许多有趣的新邻居
we've met a lot of interesting new neighbors,
其中有好邻居 也有坏邻居
but there are good neighbors and bad ones.
好邻居是这样的物体 例如
Good neighbors are, for example,
轨道稳定 有规律
objects that are in predictable orbits,
虽然走来走去 但只是在专心做自己的事
moving around, doing their own thing, minding their own business.
我们可以打量它们 朝它们挥手
We can look over and wave to them,
但它们不会对我们突然做什么事
but they're not gonna do something sudden
不会危害我们
or dangerous to us.
而坏邻居
The bad neighbors, then,
会冷不防地搞一些动作
would be things that may do something unstable.
它们可能会做一些我们始料不及的事情
They may do something that could affect us
以某种方式来影响我们
in a way that we can't predict when it's going to happen.
这也许会发生在恒星死亡或爆炸的时候
So that might be when a star dies and explodes...
或可能会发生在物体碰撞 然后一些别的东西
Or it might be when something collides and bounces off
迅速反弹到我们这边来的时候
something else and comes spinning in our direction.
所以 好坏邻居的大致划分
So classifying things roughly into good neighbors
是按照是否具有
and bad neighbors is really a classification
预测性来确定的
into predictability and unpredictability,
如果你喜欢 也可以用暴力和非暴力来划分
or violence and nonviolence if you like.
有时候 一个好邻居
Sometimes a good neighbor
会带来天外礼物
will bring a moving-in gift.
对我们来说 这应该在数十亿年前发生过
That might have happened to us, billions of years ago,
当其时 物质聚合为太阳
as the Earth was still cooling and forming
其剩余部分在形成地球并不断冷却
out of recycled material from a recycled sun.
我们可能接收了一个改变一切的礼物
We might have received a gift that changed everything.
早期的地球非常热
The early Earth was very hot,
地表水很可能都蒸发掉了
and probably any original surface water evaporated away,
所以我们认为 相当多的水
so we think that quite a bit of the water
可能来自于彗星或有冰的行星 或来自两者
may have come from either comets or icy asteroids or both.
关于地球怎么会得到这么多的水
One of the theories about how we might have gotten
世上有许多理论
so much water here on Earth
其中一个理论认为来自于外太阳系里的冰团
is from icy bodies in the outer solar system,
它们是构成太阳和行星的剩余物质
left over from the formation of the Sun and the planets,
冲入地球所在的内太阳系
crashing into our inner solar system where Earth lives
带来了一部分的水
and deliver some of that water.
根据最近的一个理论
According to one recent theory,
大约在40亿年前
about 4 billion years ago,
由于木星这些气态巨行星的万有引力
the gravity of gas giants like Jupiter
许多有冰的小行星猛烈地撞击了火星 地球和金星
sent icy asteroids slamming into Mars, Earth, and Venus.
但只有在地球上的冰进入了地幔
But only on Earth did the ice penetrate into the mantle.
水使得地球变软
The water softened the Earth
开始了板块构造这个大工程
and initiated a titanic process of plate tectonics,
从而导致山岳和海洋的出现
which led to the emergence of continents and oceans.
这和在海洋中形成生命有什么关系呢？
And what of the life that formed in the oceans?
生命所必需的有机化合物
Did organic compounds necessary for life
也是从天而降吗？
also splash down from space?
在罕见的碳质球粒陨石里 科学家找到的有机化合物
In rare meteorites called carbonaceous chondrites,
类似于曾帮助地球形成生命的
scientists have found organic compounds
那些有机化合物
like those that helped form life on Earth.
许多有机化合物的来源不同
These compounds are similar to what's been collected
但这些都与它们很相似
from many different sources,
包括南极洲微小陨石
including Antarctic micrometeorites,
星际尘埃
interstellar dust,
和美国宇航局2005年
and comet samples acquired
星尘任务所捕捉到的彗星样本
by NASA's Stardust mission in 2005.
生命的起源包含一长串的
The origin of life involves a long series
许多不同有机分子的反应
of reactions with many different organic molecules,
有机分子只含有一个碳分子
organic molecules being just ones with carbon in them,
而且 可能需要不同环境去形成
and it's possible that different circumstances are needed
不同的有机化合物
to make the different organic molecules.
它们中的一些应该是在地球形成的
Some of them might be made here on Earth,
但其它的应该在太空里更容易形成
but others might be easier to make out in space
它们被小行星或彗星带到了地球
and then bring them here to Earth on asteroids or comets.
这是可能的 如果没有我们太空邻居
It's possible that without extraterrestrial gifts
给予的天外礼物
from our neighbors in space,
地球上的生命可能永远不会出现
life on Earth might never have happened.
银河邻居们可能会帮助孕育我们
Milky Way neighbors may have helped nurture us,
但银河也有能杀死我们的东西
but the Milky Way has things that can kill us as well,
比如这一颗
with something like this:
名为葛利斯710的橙矮星
an orange dwarf named Gliese 710.
它的质量大约是太阳的60%
It's about 60% as massive as the Sun
目前离地球63光年
and is currently just 63 light-years from Earth
正在不断逼近
and getting closer.
葛利斯710几乎是
Gliese 710 appears to be heading
向着太阳系直冲过来
pretty much straight toward the solar system.
当一颗橙矮星越接近太阳系 它越值得关注
As an orange dwarf approaches the solar system, it becomes more and more significant.
在距离1光年左右时
When it's about a light-year away or less,
它就变得非常紧要了
then it becomes very important.
离地球将近1光年的是
Almost exactly 1 light-year away from Earth
一个有冰冻物体的巨大区域 它被称为奥尔特云
is a huge region of icy objects called the Oort cloud.
奥尔特云里的物体会变成彗星
The Oort cloud objects could turn into comets
如果它们离太阳足够近的话
if they were to come close enough to the Sun,
但我们通常根本看不到
but usually we don't see them at all
因为它们离太阳是如此的远
because they're so far away from the Sun.
数十亿潜在的彗星
Billions of potential comets
在等待着某些东西 比如葛利斯710
are waiting for something to give them a gravitational push,
给它们一个万有引力的推动
something like Gliese 710.
它会开始横穿奥尔特云
It'll start intersecting the Oort cloud
或至少是万有引力
or at least gravitationally disturbing it
对它干扰了130万年
in something like 1.3 million years.
如果葛利斯710靠得足够近 其万有引力
If Gliese 710 gets close enough,
会让无威胁的由冰和尘埃组成的厚块
its gravity could turn harmless chunks of ice and dust
变成向我们进攻的狂怒彗星
into rampaging comets launched at us.
对地球来说 其结果是毁灭性的
The results for Earth could be devastating.
到那时 会有一场大规模的彗星攻击
At that point, there could be a huge onslaught of comets
发生在内太阳系里
into the inner solar system
从而导致再一次灭绝
that could lead to another mass extinction.
我们不知道它将来是否发生
We don't know that that'll happen,
但它能够发生
but it could happen.
天文学家说 有86%的概率
Astronomers say there's an 86% chance
葛利斯710将会横穿奥尔特云
that Gliese 710 will barrel right through the Oort cloud.
因此 假如橙色球是葛利斯710这样的橙矮星
So if the orange ball was like an orange dwarf like Gliese 710
球瓶是奥尔特云
and the pins were the Oort cloud,
这就是要发生的事情
this is one thing that could happen.
对 但也有别的可能
All right, but here's something else that could happen.
存在14%的概率 葛利斯710会在外侧
There's a 14% chance that Gliese 710
与奥尔特云擦肩而过
is just gonna pass right by,
根本没有进入它的里面
outside the Oort cloud, not coming inside it at all.
但是 即使没有直接命中
But even without a direct hit,
这个恒星的万有引力
the effect of the star's gravity
至少能够影响到一些彗星
could disrupt at least some comets
使得它们直接冲向地球
and send them straight for us.
所以 这个恒星能驱使少许彗星冲向内太阳系
So the star could knock just a few comets toward the inner solar system.
而结果是一颗彗星撞击地球
And all it takes is one comet to hit Earth
引起一场大灾难
to cause a catastrophe.
我们需要担心的 不止是葛利斯710
We've got more than just Gliese 710 to worry about.
有超过150颗恒星
There are more than 150 stars
在接下来的200万年里 与我们近得足以干扰到我们
close enough to disturb us within the next 2 million years.
银河系里的恒星
The stars in our Milky Way galaxy
受到万有引力的制约在一起运行
are all gravitationally bound together,
所以它们沿着不同轨道运行
so they're moving in various directions,
总体上是在围绕着银河中心旋转
overall a rotation around the center of our galaxy,
但不是所有的物体都恰好如此
but not all the orbits are exactly the same.
这意味着 从我们这里看过去
That means, from our perspective,
恒星不是离我们远去 就是向我们冲来
a given star might be going away from us or toward us.
而美国宇航局估计
And NASA estimates
有超过20 000颗直径300英尺以上的
there are more than 20,000 near-Earth asteroids
近地小行星
more than 300 feet across...
比如"2005 YU55"
Like 2005 YU55,
它在2011年11月的时候
which, in November 2011,
比月亮还要靠近地球
came closer to the Earth than the Moon.
在未来的200年内 它可能会离地球更近
It might come even closer in 200 years.
被这样的石头撞击 情况会多糟糕呢？
How bad would it be to get hit by a rock like that?
想像一下二战末期的长崎市
Think about Nagasaki at the end of World War II
然后乘以四
and multiply by four.
在搜索我们这个银河角落的
As we've searched our corner of the Milky Way
坏邻居和好邻居时
for other neighbors, bad and good,
我们发现了一些非常意想不到的事情
we've found some very unexpected things.
现有证据表明 有些恒星的温度低到可以触摸
We now have evidence of stars cold enough to touch
而有些行星简直就是出自科幻小说
and planets straight out of science fiction.
对银河里我们这个地方的探测
Exploring our place in the Milky Way
引起了一个又一个的惊讶
has turned up one surprise after another.
这就像是你的邻居有一座房子
It's like there was a house in your neighborhood
但你从不知道它
that you never knew was there
你在猛然间
and that you've suddenly discovered,
才发现它在大街上
but it's just down the block.
阿尔法星
Take Alpha Centauri,
这颗半人马座里最亮的恒星
the brightest star in the constellation Centaurus
与我们最近的恒星邻居太阳
and, after the Sun, our nearest neighbor star,
距离4.3光年 即25万亿英里
4.3 light-years, or 25 trillion miles, away.
在17世纪 天文学家宣称
In the 17th century, astronomers announced
阿尔法星是双星
that Alpha Centauri was really two stars.
然后 在20世纪
Then, in the 20th century,
它被认为是三合星
it turned out to be a triple system.
阿尔法A星是典型的类太阳恒星
Alpha Centauri A is very much a sun-like star,
其质量几乎与太阳相当
nearly exactly the same mass as our Sun.
阿尔法B星则稍小一些
Alpha Centauri B is a little bit less massive.
第三颗星 比邻星
The third star, Proxima Centauri,
是一颗M型恒星
is an M-type star.
质量非常小
It's a very low-mass star,
或许只有太阳的12%
having perhaps only 12% the mass of our Sun.
它非常微弱 肉眼看不到
It's so faint that we can't see it with our unaided eye.
其它非常出名的恒星邻居
It turns out that other very well-known neighbor stars
结果也都是双星
are also multiple systems.
天狼星 距离我们8.6光年
Sirius, just 8.6 light-years away
在数千年里
and famed for thousands of years
一直以天空里最亮的星而著名
as the brightest single star in the sky,
是一颗双星
is really a binary star.
大多数恒星的质量和体积比太阳小
Most stars are less massive and smaller than our Sun,
同时 大多数恒星是双星系统
and most stars are in binary systems.
从这两方面来看 太阳稍为有点例外
In both respects, our Sun is a little bit of an exception.
大多数恒星是红矮星或褐矮星
The majority of stars are red dwarfs or brown dwarfs.
红矮星占恒星数量的70%
Red dwarfs make up 70% of the stars
不单在我们银河是这样 在宇宙里也是如此
not only in our galaxy but in the universe,
因此 即使是我们围绕太阳运行
and so even though we orbit our Sun
我们倾向于说它是神圣的恒星
and we tend to think of it as the iconic star,
但事实上 这种红矮星非常普遍
really, the red dwarfs are far more common.
对于褐矮星这些邻居
As for the brown dwarfs,
我们在20世纪90年代之前
these are neighbors we weren't sure existed
还不能肯定它们的存在
until the 1990s.
它们不太象恒星 但它们不是行星
They're not quite stars, but they're not planets.
噢 而且它们不是真的褐色
Oh, and they're not really brown either.
褐矮星是我们太阳系最神秘的居民之一
The brown dwarfs are some of the most mysterious denizens of the solar neighborhood
因为它们非常非常寒冷 所以非常黑
because they're really very, very cold, and they're very dark,
这就意味着不能发出大量的光
and that means that they don't give off a lot of light,
因此它们非常难以看到
and they're very difficult to see.
2011年 美国宇航局一架广角红外探测器
In 2011, one of NASA's space telescopes,
即简称WISE的太空望远镜
the Wide-Field Infrared Survey Explorer, or WISE,
发现了恰好位于我们地区的一系列褐矮星
found a series of brown dwarfs right in our neighborhood,
它们距离我们在9至40光年之间
between 9 and 40 light-years away,
拥有我们曾认为不可能的表面温度
with surface temperatures once considered impossible.
我们发现的这些褐矮星 其中有一颗很清凉
One of these brown dwarfs that we found is actually so cool
你可以用手去触摸它
that you could touch it with your hand.
它只有华氏80度（约27摄氏度）
It's only 80 degrees Fahrenheit,
同样的温度在地球这里 会是好天气
the same temperature as a really lovely day out here on Earth.
因此 以后的发现谁也说不清楚
And so who knows what else we'll find.
我们观察得越多 发现就越多
The more we look, the more we see.
为什么恒星的颜色不尽相同？
Why are stars so many different colors?
这是路易斯安那州巴吞鲁日的安娜.K
That's what Anna K. of Baton Rouge, Louisiana,
写信给《宇宙》咨询的问题
texted to ask The Universe.
安娜 这问题很有趣
Anna, that's a really interesting question.
总的来说 恒星颜色不尽相同
Basically, stars have slightly different colors
是因为其表面温度不同
because they have different surface temperatures.
温度不高的恒星 例如参宿四 看起来是淡红色
Cool stars like Betelgeuse look reddish,
它们只有华氏6 000 7 000度（约摄氏3 300至3 900度）
and they have temperatures of only 6,000 or 7,000 degrees Fahrenheit.
最热的恒星 比如参宿七 呈浅蓝色
The hottest stars, like Rigel, appear bluish,
它们的温度超过了20 000度（约摄氏11 000度）
and they're upwards of 20,000 degrees.
至于太阳这样的恒星
Then there are stars like the Sun,
温度为10 000 11 000度（约摄氏5 500至6 100度）
with temperatures of 10,000 or 11,000 degrees,
看起来是白色的
and they look white.
现在 初升的太阳看起来是黄色
Now, the Sun looks yellow when it's setting,
这是因为大气层的影响
but that's because of atmospheric effects.
它真正的颜色是白色
Its true color is white.
那里不是只有恒星
There are more than stars out there.
我们在本地泡的里面和外面发现了
We've discovered hundreds of neighboring planets
数以百计的行星邻居
inside and outside the local bubble.
我们通过开普勒任务 已经发现了
We have discovered a lot of exoplanet candidates
大量申报中的外星球
through a mission called Kepler
该任务利用行星经过其母恒星面前时
that is looking at essentially little eclipses,
光线变弱少许接着复原
when a planet moves in front of its parent star
这一原理
and then out,
去观察星光的微弱变化
and the light dips a little and then goes back up.
它非常难以看到
It's very difficult to see,
类似于在拉斯维加斯大道上 去寻找唯一一盏熄灭了的灯
analogous to watching for a single lightbulb going out on the Vegas Strip.
但开普勒
But Kepler is capable
是十分精确的测量高手
of doing these measurements so precisely
它能在象我们太阳一样的恒星周围
that it's able to find even planets
发现环绕运行的行星 即使它象地球那样小
as small as our own Earth around stars like our Sun.
我们发现第一颗外星球只有15年
The first exoplanet we discovered was only about 15 years ago
这很类似于我们是大街上唯一的房子
and it was very much like we were the only house on the block,
然后我们看到第一个邻居建房子
and we saw the first neighbor putting up their house,
从此之后 街区全面发展壮大
and ever since then, the entire neighborhood has grown.
外星球群落就这样在我们本地建起来了
You built up communities of other exoplanets out in our local neighborhood.
据我们所知
As far as we know,
外太阳系最靠近我们的行星邻居
our nearest planetary neighbor outside the solar system
来到了大街上 距离我们10.5光年
is just down the street, 10.5 light-years away,
它围绕着桔红色的天苑四运行
orbiting the orange star Epsilon Eridani.
这颗行星 我们肯定到不了 也不能奢望它有生命存在
This planet isn't exactly something that we could go visit and expect to find life.
我们认为这颗行星更象是
We think that this planet is more equivalent
我们太阳系里的木星
to a planet like Jupiter in our solar system
一个巨大的气态球体
a big ball of gas,
无论我们怎样去理解它
which, as we understand it anyway,
它都不是寻找生命的好去处
isn't a great place to look for life.
在稍远一点 大约200光年的地方
A little farther out, about 200 light-years,
是另外一个惊奇
is another surprise
一颗行星看起来象是
a planet that looks like something
从《星球大战》电影出来的东西
out of a Star Wars movie.
就在最近 开普勒望远镜发现了
Just recently, the Kepler telescope discovered
一颗行星围绕两个太阳运转
a planet that orbits two suns,
它被命名为开普勒-16b
and this is a planet called Kepler-16b.
这颗行星即使与"塔图因"很相似（《星球大战》中的沙漠行星）
So this planet, even though it has similarities to Tatooine,
但它完全不像天行者卢克的故土
isn't exactly like Luke Skywalker's home world.
它实际上是一个冰与气体组成的行星
It's actually a planet that's icy and gassy,
更像土星 不象我们地球
more like Saturn than our own Earth.
在这个发现之前 我们从来都不相信
Now, we were never sure, prior to this discovery,
一个行星能有两个太阳
whether you could have a planet that actually has two suns,
因此 既然现在发现了一个
and so now that we've found one,
就有可能发现更多
we know that these are possible,
这就让人很感兴趣 因为它意味着这些双星系统
and that's really interesting, because it means that these binary systems
是寻找行星的好地方
are good places to look for planets.
在2011年 天文学家揭开了我们地区
In 2011, astronomers unveiled
一种新型行星的面纱 它就是
a new kind of planet in our neighborhood
流浪行星
the homeless.
有一些行星被发现具有这样的特征
There have been some indications that there are planets to be found
它们不在围绕其母恒星的轨道上运行
that are not in orbit around their parent star.
它们开始时是围绕母恒星运行的
They started out in orbit around their parent star
但不知为什么 它们从自己的太阳系跑了出去
but somehow got ejected from their solar system,
目前在银河系里漫无目的地闲逛
and now they're wandering the galaxy aimlessly,
无家可归
without a place to call home,
对这些曾是行星 没有了母恒星的天体
so one wonders if pretty soon we'll have another
人们充满了好奇
new definition that encompasses those bodies
希望能在不久的将来
that used to be planets
有更多的认识
and no longer have a parent star.
我认为这些被驱逐的天体依然是行星
I think it's still valid to refer to these ejected bodies as planets,
因为"行星"在希腊文中就是指"流浪者"
because "planet" is the Greek word for "wanderer,"
而它们的确是在外层空间流浪
and they are certainly wandering through deep space.
从太阳系邻居身上
We've even learned new things
我们甚至能学到了许多新东西
about our solar system neighbors.
2011年夏天
In the summer of 2011,
哈勃太空望远镜拍到了以前被忽视的
the Hubble Space Telescope took the first pictures
矮行星冥王星的第四个卫星的第一张照片
of the dwarf planet Pluto's previously unsuspected fourth moon.
可能你会纳闷 冥王星不是太遥远
Now, you might wonder, Pluto is not all that distant.
发现它的第四个卫星 为什么要花费这么长的时间？
Why did it take us so long to find a fourth moon?
嗯 这是因为它非常非常小
Well, it's because it's very, very small,
直径只有10至20英里 所以它非常暗弱
only 10 to 20 miles in diameter, so it's very faint.
它只反射少量的阳光
It reflects only a little bit of the Sun's light.
这颗新卫星
The new Moon is probably
很可能就象冥王星一样 是一个严寒和死寂的世界
a frozen, lifeless world like Pluto itself.
迄今为止 所有我们最近发现的邻居
So far, all of our newly discovered neighbors
不是太热 就是太冷 根本没有我们这种生命
have been too hot or too cold to have any possibility
存在的可能
of our kind of life,
但搜索在继续着
but the search goes on.
所以 即使我们还没有做到
So even though we haven't done it yet,
但科技已经能够紧跟上
we're at this point where our technology
我们的需要
has caught up to our needs,
相信我们在不久的将来
and we're actually going to be able to start
将能踏上旅程 去发现那些与地球相似的行星
finding those planets like Earth in the really near future.
然而 要确定它们是否支持生命
However, being able to determine whether they would be
是一个难上加难的任务
supportive of life is a much more difficult task.
在我们银河角落 已发现的外行星
None of the exoplanets we've discovered
没有谁是在高举拳头恐吓我们的
in our corner of the Milky Way pose any threat to us,
但别处的一些恒星会怎么样呢？
but what about some of the stars out there?
它们中的一些会扯上我们同归于尽吗？
Could some of them die and take us with them?
银河里的我们这个地方有许多的好处
Our place in the Milky Way has a lot of plusses.
我们正处在生命可以形成的地带
We're right in the zone for life to form,
最近的恒星让我们免受宇宙射线的侵害
our closest star protects us from dangerous cosmic rays,
大多数的邻居不会打扰我们
and most of our neighbors don't disturb us.
但邻居是会翻脸的
But neighborhoods can change.
城门失火
If a fire destroys a nearby home or business,
会殃及池鱼
your home could also be damaged,
所以 想像一下 当一颗恒星
so imagine what might happen when a star
像超新星一样呜乎哀哉时发生的事情吧
goes out of business as a supernova.
这意味着它们会爆炸
That means they'll explode
把内部所有物质都抛到银河里
and throw all their innards back out to the galaxy.
爆炸的恒星创造了我们
Exploding stars created us,
恒星里的大多数重元素围绕着我们
most of the heavy elements in the stars around us,
气体在太阳系里弥漫
and the gas clouds the solar system dwells in,
但在一颗死亡中的恒星爆炸时
but it's a bad idea to be too close
离它太近 则是一个臭主意
when a dying star explodes.
超新星的爆炸
A supernova explosion
是极为强烈的爆炸
is an incredibly powerful explosion.
恒星中心急速蹦出
The core of the star bounces out
撞碎外层
and smashes into the outer layers
把它们爆裂到银河里
and blows them out into the galaxy.
所以 这些物质
So what actually happens is that material
会产生一股冲击波
gets thrown out in a shock wave that,
如果你离冲击波足够近 就会被毁灭
if you're near enough to the shock wave, would be destructive.
如果距离10光年左右
If it's 10 light-years away or so,
则正如X射线和伽马射线的一样 高能辐射会危害我们
then high-energy radiation like from X-rays and gamma rays can harm us.
它们会 比如 瓦解臭氧层
They can, for example, destroy part of the ozone layer.
具体是 辐射进来了
What happens is, the radiation comes in,
使氮分子发生分裂
disrupts nitrogen molecules.
然后氮原子与氧结合
The nitrogen atoms then combine with oxygen
生成一氧化氮
to form nitric oxide.
一氧化氮 "NO"
That nitric oxide, NO,
分裂臭氧分子 "O3"
disrupts ozone molecules, O3,
生成二氧化氮 "NO2"
and forms nitrogen dioxide, NO2.
然后二氧化氮会与氧原子结合
The nitrogen dioxide can then combine with atomic oxygen,
生成更多的一氧化氮
forming more nitric oxide,
接着分裂更多的臭氧
which then disrupts more ozone,
从而导致了滚雪球效应
which leads to a snowball effect.
因此 不到数周 臭氧层就被摧毁得差不多了
So within a few weeks, you can destroy much of the ozone layer,
此时 太阳的紫外线辐射畅通无阻
allowing the Sun's ultraviolet radiation to come in,
它会杀死
and that would then kill life
海面上的或池塘里的生命
that's on the surface layers of an ocean or in ponds.
死亡者中会包括浮游植物
That death toll would include the phytoplankton
要知道 它们是海洋食物链的基础
that are the foundation of the marine food chain
同时为地球提供了50%的氧气
and provide 50% of the Earth's oxygen,
这样就等于宣判了绝大多数生命形体的死刑
and that would spell doom for most larger forms of life,
包括我们
including us.
有一个星球灰飞烟灭的故事
One candidate for stellar extinction lies
正在本地泡外面上演
outside the local bubble, although it's been
主角是数千年来我们一直熟悉的
a familiar sight for thousands of years:
红超巨星
the red supergiant Betelgeuse.
这个恒星距离我们500至800光年
The star, between 500 and 800 light-years away
其质量是太阳的20倍
and 20 times the mass of the Sun,
构成猎户星座的右肩
forms the right shoulder of the constellation Orion.
参宿四正在走近生命的尽头
Betelgeuse is getting near the end of its life.
从1996到2011年
Between 1996 and 2011,
参宿四缩小了15%
Betelgeuse shrank by 15%
其原因目前还不清楚
for reasons that are still not understood.
这个红巨星可能会在50万年内变成超新星
The red giant may go supernova in half a million years,
或者这可能已经发生了
or it may have already happened.
可能参宿四
It's conceivable that Betelgeuse
会在今晚 明晚或下周变成超新星
will go supernova tonight or tomorrow night or next week,
但它更可能在100 000年里
but it's much more likely to become a supernova
或在数个100 000年里变成超新星
in 100,000 years or in a few 100,000 years.
在参宿四距离我们数百光年的情况下
Given that Betelgeuse is at least a few hundred light-years away,
它可能已经爆炸了
it's possible that it's already blown up,
我们之所以不知道 是因为光线还没有到达这里
and we just don't know it because the light hasn't reached us yet.
好消息是
The good news is that
哪怕猎户星座失去它的右肩
even if Orion does dislocate its shoulder,
参宿四太遥远了 危害不到我们地区
Betelgeuse is too far away to harm our neighborhood.
但另一方面 坏消息是
But then there's HR 8210,
距离我们大约150光年
about 150 light-years away,
在飞马座里的HR 8210
in the constellation Pegasus.
它不是一颗恒星 而是两颗
It's not one star but two
一颗恒星和一颗白矮星 在双轨道内相互围绕运行
a star and a white dwarf in binary orbit around each other.
这颗白矮星质量比太阳大约大15%
The white dwarf is about 15% more massive than our Sun
还没有到达向超新星演变的转折点
not at the supernova tipping point yet.
HR 8210是双星系统
HR 8210 is this binary system,
两颗恒星相互围绕运行
two stars that are orbiting one another,
已经死亡的那颗
one of which has actually already died
是一颗白矮星
and is a white dwarf.
现在 这个体系有这样的可能
Now, this system has the potential
当目前非常高温的那一颗恒星
that when the star that's very hot right now
开始垂死挣扎
starts to go through its death throes
并在死亡过程中开始膨胀时
and stars to puff up as it dies,
它会开始在这颗白矮星上面倾泻物质
it might start to pour material onto that white dwarf.
从本质上来说 这些系统就象是吞食同伴的
Essentially these systems are like zombie stars
僵尸恒星
eating their companions.
当那个正常的恒星开始变大
When that normal star starts to expand,
白矮星会开始
the white dwarf will start stealing material
偷窃同伴的物质 质量变得更加大
from its companion, becoming more massive,
假如它达到某一个不稳定的极限时
and if it reaches a certain unstable limit,
它会象"Ia型超新星"一样爆炸（热核爆炸型超新星）
it'll blow up as a type Ia supernova.
我们远到足以避开
Are we far enough away
HR 8210爆炸时带来的飞来横祸吗？
to avoid being collateral damage when HR 8210 explodes?
如果要在超新星爆炸时毫发无损
If you want to be completely safe from a supernova,
你应当至少距离它100光年远
you should be at least 100 light-years away.
10光年可能足够
10 light-years might be enough,
也可能不够
but it might not.
这要看首先杀死你的影响而定
It depends on what effect kills you first.
但这在相当长的时间里不会发生
But that won't happen for a really long time,
而到那个时候 我们已不在了
and by then we will have moved off,
同时由于星河里的一切
and it will have moved off
都有各自的发展方向
because everything in the galaxy
它也会不在了
is really on its way somewhere.
所以随着时间的流逝
So over time, that might happen,
这可能发生 但在发生的刹那
but at the point that it does,
也可能它根本不会太靠近地球
it probably won't be very close to Earth at all anymore.
不过 不要高枕无忧
But don't feel too comfortable.
HR 8210只是2002年发现的威胁
The threat of HR 8210 was only discovered in 2002.
还有多少潜在的超新星呢？
How many more potential supernovas are out there?
它们距离我们有多近？
How close are they to us?
要多久它们会爆炸？
And how soon will they explode?
形势可能不容乐观
To possibly make matters worse,
一些天文学家认为 今后在我们地区里
some astronomers say that there are a lot more supernovas
会有大量的超新星
in our neighborhood's future.
我们太阳系围绕银河运行的速度
Our solar system orbits our galaxy at a different rate
与旋臂的不同
than the spiral arms do.
这意味着 最终我们将进入一个旋臂里
That means, eventually, we're gonna enter a spiral arm,
而那里有大量的更大质量的恒星
and because there is a lot more massive stars there,
它们中的一些会终结自己的生命
some of them will be ending their lives,
产生超新星 对地球上的生命造成
creating supernovae and posing a greater threat
更大威胁
to life on Earth.
在今晚 银河里的我们这个地方
Still, our place in the Milky Way
还是安全的 而且
is secure for tonight
太空充斥着被称为宇宙射线的辐射
Space is filled with radiation known as cosmic rays.
我们有大量时间去探索更多
plenty of time for more exploration
也会有更多的惊奇
and more surprises.
我们居住在多变的地区
We live in a pretty diverse neighborhood,
事实上 事物正在变化
actually, and things are changing.
银河不会一成不变
The galaxy is not a static place,
所以它在亿万年里将会是
so it's gonna be an interesting place to see
一个有趣的地方
in a billion years.